Mikhail Fominykh, PhD

Personal information

Address: Waldemar Aunes vei 10B, 7027 Trondheim, Norway

Mobile phone: (+47) 48603627

Email: <u>mihail.fominyh@gmail.com</u>

Date/place of birth: 16.07.1984, Russia Citizen/Resident: Russia/Norway

Homepage: http://mikhailfominykh.com/

My professional career has been a journey from developing educational multimedia resources to studying innovative learning methods and designing learning tools, to building networks for organizing joint research studies and acquiring grants for international projects. I seek opportunities to realise my enthusiasm for grant proposals and R&D projects and develop my teaching skills.

Selected projects

[2015-now] R&I project: Wearable Experience for Knowledge Intensive Training, http://wekit.eu/

- Organization: Europlan UK ltd
- Funded by: EU under Horizon 2020 programme, call ICT-20-2015, http://ec.europa.eu/
- Responsibilities: original idea, proposal coordination, leading work package "Roadmap, Exploitation, and Business Impact", research, and dissemination

[2016-now] R&D project: Active Learning Module for Emergency Management Professionals using VR

- Organization: Molde University College
- Funded by: Norgesuniversitetet https://norgesuniversitetet.no/
- Responsibilities: pedagogical and tech. design, programming, evaluation, and research

[2015-**now**] R&D project: Virtuell samhandling

- Organization: Mikhail Fominykh one-person company org. nr. 997 025 849
- Funded by: NTNU «Innovative utdanning» programme
 http://www.ntnu.no/toppundervisning/utviklingsprosjekter-2015-2016
- Responsibilities: design of 3D educational environment, web design, and technical support

[2015-**now**] R&D project: Virtuell Velferdsteknologi

- Organization: Mikhail Fominykh one-person company org. nr. 997 025 849
- Funded by: Trondheim Kommune, https://helsedirektoratet.no/velferdsteknologi/
- Responsibilities: design of 3D educational environment and training scenarios

[2009-now] R&D project: vAcademia http://voutu.be/TA1UhcR2 X8

• Organization: Multimedia System Lab, Volga State University of Technology (VSUT), Russia Responsibilities: Research, testing, and dissemination

[2015–2016] R&D project: Emergency Management Training with Virtual Reality

- Organization: Molde University College
- Responsibilities: pedagogical and tech. design, programming, evaluation, and research

[2011–2013] Research project: CoCreate http://www.cocreat.eu/

- Organization: Department of Computer and Information Science, NTNU
- Funded by: EU under Life Long Learning programme
- Responsibilities: design of 3D educational environment, instructional design, research, tutoring

[2011–2014] R&D project: Cultural Awareness in Military Operations

- Organization: Mikhail Fominykh one-person company org. nr. 997 025 849
- Funded by: ADL, Norwegian armed forces
- Responsibilities: design of 3D educational environment, research, and technical support

[2010–2011] R&D project on serious games: TARGET http://www.reachyourtarget.org/

- Organization: Programme for Learning with ICT, NTNU
- Funded by: EU under FP7 programme
- Responsibilities: Organization of community events in a 3D environment, website support



Academic experience

[2015-**now**] Associate Professor, Molde University College, Norway http://www.himolde.no/

- Project: Emergency Management Training with Virtual Reality
- Project: Active Learning Module for Emergency Management Professionals using Virtual Reality

[2014-**now**] Adjunct Professor, VSUT, Russia http://volgatech.net/

Teaching: Introduction to Virtual Reality

[2012–2014] Postdoctoral research fellow, Programme for Learning with ICT, NTNU, Norway

Research project: CoCreate http://www.cocreat.eu/

[2007–2012] PhD Research Fellow at Program for Learning with ICT, NTNU, Norway

- R&D project on serious games: TARGET http://www.reachyourtarget.org/
- R&D project: Virtual City of Yoshkar-Ola, http://virtyola.ru/
- Project: Travel in Europe, funded by EU cultural heritage
- R&D Project: Virtual Campus of NTNU http://slurl.com/secondlife/NTNU/

Teaching Experience

[2013-**now**] Joint European Summer School on Technology Enhanced Learning http://jtelsummerschool.eu/

- Eight workshops and on research design, community building, and industrial training
- One lecture on EU funding

[Fall 2015] VSUT, Russia: Introduction to Virtual Reality course

• Responsibilities: lectures, practical exercises, and assessment

[2008–2014] NTNU, Norway: Cooperation Technologies and Social Media course

Course design, lectures, practical exercises, and assessment

[2013] Erasmus+ teaching mobility

Series of guest lectures at the University of Oulu, Finland

[2011–2012] EU CoCreat project https://cocreat.wordpress.com/

Design and tutoring in two international distant courses

R&D Experience

[2014-**now**] Project Manager, Europlan UK Ltd, UK http://europlan-uk.eu/

- Initiator and co-leader of Horizon 2020 project WEKIT http://wekit.eu/, funded by EU
- Manager of development project Information sharing portal for the Body of European Regulators for Electronic Communications http://berec.europa.eu/, funded by BEREC Office

[2011-**now**] Mikhail Fominykh one-person company org. nr. 997 025 849

- Project: Virtuell samhandling
- Project: Virtuell Velferdsteknologi
- Project: Cultural Awareness in Military Operations, funded by ADL, Norwegian Defence Forces

[2006–2007] Designer, Multimedia System Lab, VSUT, Russia http://www.mmlab.ru/

- Project: "E-learning resources for Chemistry" funded by Russian Ministry of Education http://fcior.edu.ru/about.page (in Russian only)
- Project: "Virtual Collaborative Learning Environments" funded by Russian Ministry of Education http://www.mmlab.ru/projects/collab/collab.shtml
- Project: "Virtual City of Yoshkar-Ola" funded by VSUT http://virtyola.ru/
 Responsibilities: research, project management, 2D and 3D design and animation, programming

[2001–2007] Programmer, Several IT companies, Russia

Education

[2008–2012] Department of Computer and Information Science, NTNU, Norway

■ PhD Thesis: "Collaborative work on 3D educational content" * <u>DiVA</u>

[2001–2006] Faculty of Information Technologies and Computer Engineering, VSUT, Russia

- Diploma Thesis: "Designing 3D Virtual Environment for Learning Arts"
- Average grade: 4.75 (min. passing grade 3, max. grade 5)

[1996-2000] Art school, Russia

• Subjects: Graphics, Painting, Composition, Decorative Arts, History of Visual Art

Awards and Grants

[Dec 2015] Project: Active Learning Module for Emergency Management Professionals using VR

Granted by: Norgesuniversitetet, NOK 450.000

[Aug 2015] Research and Innovation project: WEKIT http://wekit.eu/

• Granted by: EU Horizon 2020 Programme EUR 2.753.144, grant no 687669

[2014] Personal grant to participate training events on writing EU proposals

- Lab Surfing Workshop, Italy https://fet-eye.eu/milan-may-2014
- Blue Sky conference, Hungary https://fet-eye.eu/bs-2014
- Science Incubator Summer School, France https://fet-eye.eu/siss-2014
- Granted by: EYE, coordination and support project funded by the EU

[Apr 2014] Personal grant to teach at the Tenth Joint European Summer School on Technology Enhanced Learning, Malta

• Granted by: TESEO lab, NTNU http://www.prolearn-academy.org/Events/summer-school-2014

[Sep 2013] Demo special recognition: Virtual Afghan Village as a Low-Cost Environment for Training Cultural Awareness in a Military Context

• Granted by: European Association of Technology Enhanced Learning http://ectel2013.cs.ucy.ac.cy/index.php/conference/papers-and-demos-awards

[Aug 2013] Personal grant to conduct a trans-national access research project at the University College London, UK

 Granted by: VISIONAIR, project funded by the EU http://www.infra-visionair.eu/accepted-projects.html

[May 2013] Audience Choice Award at the Ninth Joint European Summer School on Technology Enhanced Learning

 Granted by: European Association for Technology Enhanced Learning http://www.prolearn-academy.org/Events/summer-school-2013

[Mar 2013] Personal grant to give lectures at the University of Oulu, Finland

 Granted by: ERASMUS Teacher Mobility program http://ec.europa.eu/education/tools/llp_en.htm#tab-4

[May 2011] Personal grant to participate in the Seventh Joint European Summer School on Technology Enhanced Learning

 Granted by: European Association for Technology Enhanced Learning http://www.prolearn-academy.org/Events/summer-school-2011

[Mar 2011] Outstanding paper award: Virtual Research Arena: Presenting Research in 3D Virtual Environments

 Granted by: Association for the Advancement of Computing in Education http://www.editlib.org/j/GLEARN/v/2011/n/1/?show_awards_only=true

[Jun 2009] Outstanding paper award: Virtual Campus in the Context of an educational Virtual City: a Case Study

 Granted by: Association for the Advancement of Computing in Education http://www.editlib.org/j/EDMEDIA/v/2009/n/1/?show awards only=true

Selected publications

Mikhail Fominykh, Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland, Monica Divitini, and Sobah Abbas Petersen: "Boundary Objects in Collaborative Work and Learning," *Information Systems Frontiers*, ISSN: 1387-3326, EISSN: 1572-9419, 2015, Springer, pp. 1–18. doi> 10.1007/s10796-015-9579-9.

Mikhail Fominykh, Andrey Smorkalov, Mikhail Morozov, and Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland: "3D Virtual Worlds as a Fusion of Immersing, Visualizing, Recording, and Replaying Technologies," in D. Sharma et al. eds., *Fusion of Smart, Multimedia and Computer Gaming Technology: Research, Systems and Perspectives*, 2015, Springer, Intelligent Systems Reference Library 84 ISSN: 1868-4394, pp. 137–171. doi>10.1007/978-3-319-14645-47

Andrey Smorkalov, **Mikhail Fominykh**, and Mikhail Morozov: "Collaborative Work and Learning with Large Amount of Graphical Content in a 3D Virtual World Using Texture Generation Model Built on Stream Processors," *International Journal of Multimedia Data Engineering and Management* (IJMDEM), Volume 5, Issue 2, 2014, IGI-Global, ISSN: 1947-8534, EISSN: 1947-8542, pp. 18–40. doi>10.4018/ijmdem.2014040102.

Mikhail Fominykh and Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland: "Educational Visualizations in 3D Collaborative Virtual Environments: a Methodology," *International Journal of Interactive Technology and Smart Education (ITSE)*, Volume 9, issue 1, 2012, Emerald, ISSN: 1741-5659, pp. 33–45. doi>10.1108/17415651211228086

Mikhail Fominykh, Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland, and Monica Divitini: "Creative Collaboration in a 3D Virtual World Conducting Educational Activities, Designing Environments, and Preserving Results," in D. G. Sampson et al. eds., *Digital Systems for Open Access to Formal and Informal Learning*, 2014, Springer, pp. 257–274. doi>10.1007/978-3-319-02264-2 16

Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland, **Mikhail Fominykh**, Ramin Darisiro, Anders I. Mørch, and David Hansen: "Preparing for International Operations and Developing Scenarios for Inter-cultural Communication in a Cyberworld: A Norwegian Army Example," in Marina Gavrilova et al. eds., *Transactions on Computational Science (TCS)*, 2014, Springer, LNCS 8490 ISSN 0302-9743, Issue XXIII, pp. 118–138. doi>10.1007/978-3-662-43790-2 7

Mikhail Fominykh: "Creating and Retrieving Knowledge in 3D Virtual Worlds," in U. Gehmann and M. Reiche eds., *Real Virtuality: About the Destruction and Multiplication of World*, 2014, <u>Transcript</u>, pp. 337–368.

Mikhail Morozov, Alexey Gerasimov, **Mikhail Fominykh**, and Andrey Smorkalov: "Asynchronous Immersive Classes in a 3D Virtual World: Extended Description of vAcademia," in M. Gavrilova et al. eds., *Transactions on Computational Science (TCS)*, 2013, Springer LNCS 7848, Issue XVI, pp. 81–100. doi>10.1007/978-3-642-38803-3 5

Mikhail Fominykh, Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland, Leif Martin Hokstad, and Mikhail Morozov: "Repositories of Community Memory as Visualized Activities in 3D Virtual Worlds," in *the 47th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS)*, Waikoloa, HI, USA, January 6–9, 2014, IEEE, pp. 678–687. doi>10.1109/HICSS.2014.90

Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland, **Mikhail Fominykh**, Ramin Darisiro, and Anders I. Mørch: "Training Cultural Awareness in Military Operations in a Virtual Afghan Village: A Methodology for Scenario Development," in Ralph H. Sprague, Jr. ed., *the 46th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS)*, Wailea, HI, USA, January 7–10, 2013, IEEE, pp. 903–912. doi>10.1109/HICSS.2013.571

Mikhail Fominykh, Ekaterina Prasolova-Førland, and Monica Divitini: "Learning Computer-Mediated Cooperation in 3D Visualization Projects," in Yuhua Luo ed., *the 9th International Conference on Cooperative Design, Visualization and Engineering (CDVE)*, Osaka, Japan, September 2–5, 2012, Springer, LNCS 7467, ISSN: 0302-9743, p. 65–72. doi>10.1007/978-3-642-32609-79

Active memberships in scientific program committees

- Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine, Journal, invited reviewer 2016
- Computer & Education, International Journal, invited reviewer 2016
- New Review of Hypermedia and Multimedia Journal, invited reviewer, 2015
- International Journal of Artificial Intelligence in Education, invited reviewer, 2015
- ILRN, member of the Program Committee, 2015, 2016
- IEEE Multimedia, invited reviewer, 2015
- IEEE Communications Magazine, invited reviewer, 2014
- ISM, member of the Technical Program Committee 2014
- <u>Journal of Educational Technology & Society</u>, invited reviewer, 2014
- TEL Summer School, member of the Programme Committee, 2014, 2015
- ICALT, member of the Virtual Worlds in Education and Training track Program Committee 2014, 2015
- <u>Program Board in Learning and Collaboration Technologies 2014, 2015</u>
- <u>SES STET</u>, member of the International Program Committee, <u>2014</u>, <u>2015</u>, <u>2016</u>
- SCITEED, member of the Scientific Committee, 2014
- Behaviour & Information Technology Journal, invited reviewer, 2013, 2016
- SLACTIONS, member of the Scientific Committee 2013, 2014

Other professional skills

Languages:

- English: fluent
- Norwegian (Bokmål): good
- Russian: native

Other skills:

- Motivation and commitment
- Multidisciplinary competences and interests
- Communication and teamwork

Computer skills:

- Operating systems: Windows and Android
- Programming: C-based languages, Pascal-based languages
- Web design: HTML, CSS
- 2D Graphics: Adobe Photoshop and Illustrator
- 3D Graphics: 3ds Max, Maya, SketchUp, and Second Life